So yes uh today's suta is suta 4720
um the beauty of the land or the most
beautiful woman in the land.
So um thus I have heard at one time the
blessed one was staying among uh sumbas
in the market town of sumbas named
sedaka. There he addressed the monks.
There he addressed the monks.
Just as monks, if people were together
saying the beauty of the land, the
beauty of the land, a great crowd would
assemble. That beauty of the land is the
most skilled in dancing, most skilled in
singing. When that beauty of the land
dances and sings monks, an even larger
crowd would gather to watch her.
Then a man would come desiring to live
not to die, desiring happiness and
averse to pain.
And if someone were to say to him,
"Now a good man, this full oil bowl must
be carried by you between the great
crowd and that beautiful woman, and a
man with raised sword will follow you uh
right behind you. Whenever you spill
even a little bit of oil,
uh your head will be cut off."
So what do you think monks? Would that
man not attend to the old bowl and allow
negligence outwardly? And um here I
added passages from u the uh agama sing
aama parallel
which kind of adds a bit um more
description. So in Nagma he says what do you think
So in Nagma he says what do you think
monks that man holding the oil bowl
could he fail to keep in mind the oil
bowl fail to keep in mind the killer and
instead watch the performer and the
crowd or not?
Then the monks obviously replied, "Well,
surely not, Venipus."
In Agama, they said, "Surely not the
Lord. He will unify. He unifies his
mind. He thinks about the old ball. And
among the worldly beautiful form and the
great crowd, he will walk slowly
through, not daring to glance or look
around."
This simile monks has been made to
convey a meaning. And the meaning is
the full ball oil ball monks is the term
for recollectedness of the body.
And uh Agama says uh adds to this saying
if there is a shaman or Brahmana correct
in the body and self-respecting
unifying his mind and thoughts not
giving attention to the sounds and forms
i.e. sense objects well collecting all
mental phenomena dwelling in the
recollectedness of the body that one is
my disciple one who follows my teaching.
So then the Buddha continues saying
therefore monks you should train
recollectness of the body will be
developed by us made much of made our
vehicle our foundation established
accumulated and well undertaken. Thus
indeed monks you should train.
Um this is where the pali suta ends but
then the um agama has quite a bit more
including some um interesting verses at
the end.
So the p agama continues saying what is
called monks a monk who is correcting
the body self-respecting unifying his
mind and thoughts not giving attention
to the sounds and forms eyes and objects
while collecting all mental phenomena
and dwelling in the recollectness of the
body. Well, it's a monk who is
recollecting body within the body,
feeling within the feeling, chitta
within chitta, dhamma within dhamas. So,
it's a monk who practices the satipana
with diligent effort, right
understanding and right
recollectiveness, subduing worldly
craving and sorrow.
This is called the monk that is correct
in the body, self-respecting, unifying
his mind and thoughts and so on. It
repeats it.
Um so when the the Buddha said that he
immediately followed with a verse saying
uh unifying mind with right
recollectness protect
uh and uphold the old bowl guard one's
own mind accordingly in a place not yet
reached extremely difficult to pass
through superior and subtle what all
Buddhas have spoken the doctrine of a
sharp sword one should unify one's mind
diligently guard and uphold it no such
ordinary men in the matters of
negligence can enter such a state the
teaching of non-negligence.
So the Buddha having spoken the discus
um monks rejoiced and practiced
accordingly. So it's a it's a short suta
So it's a it's a short suta
uh and the um
go back to this. So yeah uh the obvious
points you know they come up when you when you
you know they come up when you when you
look at the suta. Well I remember even
even like when I was like long time ago
when I started practicing when I was a
layman um when I came across this suta
and u as I said before usually most of
us would have kind of arrived at
Buddhism and the dharma and the sutras
u through
some interest or idea of meditation.
the the concentration practices or
whatever whatever vague ideas we all
would have started with that was kind of
our framework that that then eventually
through circumstances or who knows what
else kind of directed us towards the
sutras and so on. But the problem with
that was that even when the sutas uh
were being read back then you would have
been reading them I know I did through
the same kind of uh framework and ideas
of uh concentration practices focus and
meditation. So I remember when I read
this suta um it was kind of like aha
okay so uh you must focus on the on the
bowl on your head in the same sense you
must like really really kind of intently
concentrate on it. That's how you
survive. That's how you don't spill it.
And I think uh I think um I mean I'm
pretty sure in ter it's often used that
suda to support the ideas of focusing
practices. And I think also in ganka as well it's
And I think also in ganka as well it's
been uh it's been singled out. But then
I remember thinking I was like, "Yeah,
but hold on. If you actually stop and
think about it, if you were to have
something on top of your head
and um
have to walk through a
crowd or even just do it as a test, just
walk through your room, cluttered room
with chairs and and stuff and people
around like would you be concentrating
on the thing on your head?" It's like,
would I be would I be needing to
concentrate on the on the ball on top of
my head? It's like, well, no, because
it's already there. It's known. It's
there. It's felt there. I don't need to
I don't need to like double down in my
ways of attending to it. Um, in order to
like not spill it like it's already
there. It's already felt. Quite the
opposite. I shouldn't be concentrating
on that. I should actually be more aware
of the broader sense of balance.
uh more aware of the broader sense of my
environment. Uh more aware of where I'm heading,
Uh more aware of where I'm heading,
where I'm going as opposed to just shut
that all out and just focus hard on the
sensations of the top of my head where
the ball touches my skin or something.
It's like, oh yeah, and not just that
that practically wouldn't work if you
were to try it. you realize, oh, that's
why the suta goes into this elaborate
description of the most beautiful woman
in the world with the most beautiful
voice and the most beautiful dance and
everybody from the country gathers. So
it's like to create the environment well
to to show you the environment that you
live in which is the environment of
sense objects that are always enticing
that are always u pressuring you to look
to taste to touch to think about to to
choose to act towards
and then you have a a a bowl on top of
your head. So it's like oh so the suta
is really intentionally contrasting that
that's the simile. It's not like, oh,
just focus on the top of the on top of
your head where the ball is and doesn't
really matter what's around you. It's
like, no, no, no. The whole point is you
have to walk through the crowd. The
crowd that's not a a a neutral,
indifferent crowd, the crowd of rowdy
sense uh senses, objects, other people
and so on. Uh and you are the one who
mustn't spill the oil from the bowl.
So if you try doing that uh through the
practice of sensation watching or
concentrating or whatever
nostrils of breathing oh you will spill
it even before you reach the crowd like
in no time you'll bump into somebody or
somebody will bump into you. So the way
you would actually have to practically
walk through it would be not losing the
sense of balance, not losing the sense
of uh the danger most importantly that
there is a man with a drawn sword
because uh you won't forget about the
ball on top of your head
unless you choose to go and do something
else and distract yourself with it. and
you would choose to do something else
and distract yourself with it when you
forget about the danger of forgetting
about the ball on top of your head which
is somebody will cut your head off. So
if the danger is there the awareness the
the the recollectedness the
nonforgetfulness of that ball will be
there. So then what you actually paying
attention to is where you're going
uh what you're choosing to do. Are you
choosing to turn your head and look? Are
you choosing to stop and and start
dancing yourself because it's just so
amazing? Not just that you would be paying
Not just that you would be paying
attention to what you're doing, you
would also be paying attention and
trying to foresee what other people
around you will do it that might affect
you. Like you can be as careful as you want
Like you can be as careful as you want
walking through, but if you are taking
the course in the crowd where it's like
where men are even rowdier, even
crazier, there is a good chance somebody
will just bump into you. doesn't matter
how careful you are and you'll spill the
oil and your head will be cut off. So
you're foreseeing that foreseeing that
certain actions although might not be
necessarily unh wholesome like well
going left or right makes no difference
uh certain actions might actually take
you in a worse environment where you
won't be able to protect your mind in
the same sense if you would have avoided
it. So you would be foreseeing the
behavior and so on where it's riskier
and then you wouldn't go that way
because of it because why? because the
danger of spilling the oil.
So that danger is what gives you um the
context to all your actions. Um so it's
it's when you when when you when you
start thinking about it you realize as I
said the whole simile the way what it
emphasizes but even if you just
practically do it put something on your head and try
do it put something on your head and try
walking and uh you will realize oh so
it's actually about contrasting that
kind of uh uh discrepancy of the the
senses senses pulling you and what you
have to ma uh maintain and be uh
nonforgetful of because if you just Try
concentrating and focusing on the ball
as hard like really be absorbed in it as
the modern meditation techniques in
terabad teaches you. You will lose the
sight of what's around you. I mean
that's kind of exactly well for many
people that seems like a like a purpose
of the meditation
which is like it's probably not
incidental that that these uh practices
would be kind of a default of an
ignorant mind because see although the
the bowl with oil implies the danger of
somebody cutting your head off if you
don't forget that there is a man behind
you. doubling down and focusing hard on
the ball will distract you even from the
danger will make you not feel the danger
anymore because you you you have been
sufficiently self-hypnotized so to
speak. So that's why these practices
would be popular because they offer a
seeming escape from the problem by
really just
fortifying your attention away from the
danger. Not by fixing the danger, not by
uprooting the danger.
So um
so yeah then um as the as the uh we can
go back to the
to the actual suta part. Yeah. So then
as the agama adds to that.
So it's like when the monks replied they
like well no he wouldn't be careless. He
would unify his mind and he would think
about a bowl uh uh and among the worldly
beautiful form and the great crowd he
wouldn't be daring to glance or look
around. He wouldn't be daring to be
engaged with it which would imply
forgetting about the bowl. Um and even
when the Buddha asked that even in the
palood he says what do you think monks
would that man not attend to the oil
ball and allow negligence outwardly?
That's what Pali says. So, so it's like
allowing the negligence outwardly. It's
what takes you away
from the right balance.
What takes you away from the from the
recollectiveness of the body. It's not
like you not being focusing hard enough
on sensations or something. So, it's
like if you don't choose the negligence,
you are staying on the right level. You
are not spilling the oil. And um
so so yeah, like when I asked this
question to people, yeah, one of the
replies was was was quite interesting
because the person that replied says
they actually had to do something
similar. They used to work in a in a
Chinese hot pot restaurant and had to
carry a bowl of hot oil across the
restaurant floor during the working
hours when there are children running
around people getting off the tables and
so on. So it was like a and as it
happened uh as I said like at that time they were
uh as I said like at that time they were
practicing the very typical modern
concentration methods and practices
going on retreats and and similar. So
while they were carrying the ball, they
actually tried to do their idea of the
Buddhist practice. So they were focusing
on um on the fingers of holding the bowl
and on the soles of your feet and
mindfully walking and almost instantly
basically realized that they lost the
sight of the danger of spilling the oil
on a child's head. And that scared them
even more
because you focus and everything seems
fine and calm and then you just wake up
and realize what environment you are
still in. What are the implications? And
then on top of it, you obviously
probably realize that you haven't been
paying attention to the children and
what's coming your way as much because
you were so focused on your own
sensations. So, so that person said that they pretty
So, so that person said that they pretty
much had to decide that while they're
working at that place, they'll put the
Buddhist practice. They still didn't see
the the practice um of those
concentration prayers as a problem, but
they realized that they had to put it
aside and they can't do it in that
environment. So they'll do it uh when they go back
So they'll do it uh when they go back
home or something because it was just
incompatible with being aware of your
surroundings uh what's coming your way and being
uh what's coming your way and being
aware of the danger and implications of
what would happen if you were to
actually hurt somebody and cause
injuries with that oil.
So they said they almost instantly
realized that um that it won't work. And
um all they then did is like they simply
kept reminding themselves or or not not
not being able to forget, not trying to
forget that splashing the oil meant
danger. Splashing the oil meant
consequences. Splashing the oil meant lawsuits.
Splashing the oil meant lawsuits.
So this uh as I said like that seemingly
abstract context actually became very
real and directed all the subsequent
actions. how they walked, what they
looked at, how they carried the ball,
how they lifted the ball, what they
thought about, what they planned,
everything was unified through the
recollection of the right context of the
danger or and implications of certain
actions. Um so
Um so
so basically yeah like you could see
that that um you could see this example
as I said before even in the most in the
most mundane mundane situations and it's
only because as I said most of us would
have um arrived at the sutras and
started reading the sutras after you
already picked up these views of what
meditation is and the practices and the
ideas and hopes and expectations what
will come out of it.
then we read the sutas or been reading
the sutas through those um through that
lens through those kind of tinted
glasses so to speak. But um if you were
to take a non Buddhist and give them
these examples and ask them to do it and
then ask them to describe how they would
do it at no point in time would any of
them resort to describing sensation
watching, hard focusing, intense focus,
concentration where everything else
disappears. in all these contemporary
descriptions of what what meditation is
in Janna, which is basically just uh as
we said so many times before a form of
self hypnosis. If you just do a little
research and see what self hypnosis is
um and people that do it and how they do
it, it's like verbatim. It's just
exactly the same practice. Like you you
might use different terms and and and
and labels to it, but you're doing
exactly the same thing, which is taking
you completely the opposite way of where
you should be. Um if you follow the
example at the simile of the suta of the
context of the danger they would then
guide your actions and your choices and
certainly the level of your engagement
with sensuality would also be be kept in
check. So So
um
what else can we mention? Oh yeah so
like um I did uh I did ask that in the
past as well. So it's like
attention and concentration.
So it's like what's the difference
between uh attention and concentration?
Like does does attention mean
concentration or are you attending
things without needing to concentrate on
them? And uh yeah, it's kind of obvious to
And uh yeah, it's kind of obvious to
anybody that's been listening to our
talks, but uh maybe to new people that
come to watch this, you could think
about it yourself before you hear what
I'm about to answer and see if you could
actually see for yourself what the
difference is. Like when I'm attending
to something and when I'm concentrating
on something and um
as I have said like in the earlier talks
like so attention is not concentration.
So you're always attending to something
directly indirectly basically there is
always attention is always resting on
something but that's not concentrating.
Concentrating is choosing to to
artificially emphasize that which you
have already been attending.
So it's in a way it's like concentration
is a way of overattending
which is usually done because you have
one or the other reason to do so. So in
other words, you would have picked up
the views that focusing uh like beaming
down onto the object of your of your
meditation or whatever is super
important because you know the whole
tradition tells you it is. So you choose
to artificially over attend something
until everything else disappears from
your view. So it's like narrowing down.
So it's completely the opposite from
surmounting and and and including and
that uh eagata that elevation that that
the sutas talk about.
So um
so yeah in the in the practice of
concentration for one reason or the
other you choose to single out an idea
or an object and then really like double
down in your in your ways of attending
it. So, so you could think of like um
attention does not need concentration
but there is no concentration without
attention and um
and um
obviously you know to some degree
dealing with stuff sometimes you need to
attend something more at the expense of
something else. So that's already a
concentration. So concentration is not
in and of itself inherently bad. It's
just a nature. It's like a it's like
what mind does.
um it's it's a nature of the experience
and to some degree you are attending
stuff and I said if you have a reason to
do you would be like like increasing
that so it's not like that it's
concentrating is always bad but when it
comes to the practice of the dharma
where you need to keep that broad
picture in the mind the sense of danger
the implication uh implications the the
the the counterpart the sense objects
that are trying to pull you and narrow
down your perspective and so on that's
like oh concentration is actually kind
of the the the tool of sensuality. It's
how sensuality works. Like it it
naturally sucks you in, concentrates
you, makes you forget about everything
else. It makes you forget what's
important to you as well. That's why the
Buddha would often talk about frequently
recollecting those topics and
perceptions that are important to you as
somebody who wants to practice rightly.
Um and recollection and recollectedness
and nonforggetfulness and that memory is
not something you can concentrate on.
Quite the opposite. By unfocusing from
things, by unfocusing from the
sensations of the top of your head, you
become aware of what's already there.
The big picture, the rowdy crowd, the
need to walk through it, the man be
behind you with a sword. It's like, oh,
so I shall maintain the practice of
unfocusing. Whenever my attention the naturally
Whenever my attention the naturally
rested stuff starts being sucked in
further either through sensuality or
through artificial uh contemporary
concentration meditation practices I
shall unattend to that extent to stay on
the right level.
Um
so so then as the suta says um so the
the the simile obviously the the
equivalent of the uh bowl of oil is the
recollectiveness of the body
and uh
um as I described that before well many
times before in so many talks uh the
actual body is not something as a as a
collection of um the actual body as a
sallayata as basically the sense organs
as a as a unity which is your body. So
eyes, nose, ears, sense of touch, tongue
obviously uh well you can't attend your
sense organs. You cannot concentrate on
them. You cannot single them out as
objects because they're always negative
to the to to its corresponding objects.
So eye can never see itself. Doesn't
matter how hard it tries to look. Simply
it's always behind the look. tongue can
never taste itself and obviously body
can never touch itself so to speak. So
it's the the the actual body that you're
mindful of is not something you can
directly attend to
because the sallayatana
that that need to be surmounted is is
not something that appears that can
appear as an object of of of your
attention and perception. So it's always
something indirect. It's always
something peripheral. It's always
something that can only be known. And
that's exactly the point. It's like
if the body
can only be known peripherally, then you
realize, okay, so it's already there.
The only time I'm not like I'm it's not
that I'm not aware of the body if I
haven't been focusing or trying to
figure it out hard enough. It's like I
become unaware of the body when I choose
to be negligent towards things
outwardly. How the suta says. So that's
why the virtue that we often talk about
and sense restraint outlines the body,
outlines the mind for you. Outlines the
entire domain of four satipatanas for
the practice.
Um it's not a practice you can do
instead of virtue instead of withdrawal
or from the outwardly negligence.
So it's not it's not simply not
optional. The whole the whole the whole
point of it is that whether you you you
are making the effort to do it to figure
it out unless you withdrawn from the
sense objects unless you are not
choosing to go into the crowd and start
dancing and and and singing yourself and
looking at the at the enticing sites. So
unless you stop doing those things, you
won't be mindful. Doesn't matter how
hard you try to to outline the body and
see it peripherally and so on. So that's
like like but on the other hand if you
are actually stop engaging in the acts
of the external negligence even if you
don't make the effort internally to to
to think about you know the body and
make all the sense out of the things we
say you will be closer to that because
you're not as I said you're not
obstructing it through all these
unnecessary external engagements that
are rooted in greed aversion and
delusion. So that's like a training in that
So that's like a training in that
peripheral recognition of what's already
there. The sense of body as experience
as a whole, not a specific sensation
which is just a sense of touch because
the body is already there. So training
in the peripheral recognition on the
basis of virtue and your choice to not
follow the enticing sense objects. Uh
that's how you you are you're mindful of
the body. That's how you practice the
recollectiveness correctly, the
nonforgetfulness. So, so that's the that's the uh pretty
So, so that's the that's the uh pretty
much as I said the practice recognizing
the danger
the context around you like you won't be
able to forget about the a bowl full of
oil on top of your head even if you want
to. So this is the same recognizing the
So this is the same recognizing the
dangers of of losing the sight of that
peripheral body of that indirect body
and falling into a trap of of being
being controlled by the sense objects
whereby you think you're observing your
body where you're just observing just
another among the sense objects. It's
just like a being fully sucked into the
central domain. That's the danger.
That's the peril. That's like the man
cutting your head off. So uh like people
have asked like also how does the the
the cutting your head off how does that
translate that danger that kind of
immediate death how does that translate
to recollectness of the body well
translates to like you know in the other
sutas when the Buddha said uh those who
are not mindful who are not recollected
here they are as if dead already
that's how it translates to as I just
described you are you are within the
central domain
by not being recollected properly on the
right level by being overly uh uh uh
focused or overly negligent or or overly
concentrated due to whatever views you
might be carrying about the special
meditation experiences and calming you
get from it. You are you you're not
leaving the central domain. You're very
well and thoroughly still bound by it.
And that's like being in a in a car
that's flying down a hill in a bus. So
although you're technically still alive
like you're dead basically there is no
chance of you surviving that situation.
So that's exactly what the Buddha meant.
Those who are not recollected are as if
dead already.
Um and that's like the um um
where was it now?
Yeah the verses that the Buddha adds
towards the end in that in the Yagam. So
it's like
what is a monk who is correcting the
body and self-respecting unifying his
mind and thoughts not giving attention
to the sounds and forms I sense objects
well collecting all mental phenomena. So
correcting the body means that means
virtues means not having not being
engaging in in things that in in
breaking the precepts
upright uh self-respecting means what we
often talk about authentic transparent
having respect basically for for your
values for what you know is valuable not
ignoring that
that's how you unify your mind that
which is outlined by uh being protected
not being distracted from through your
choices of negligence
uh choosing to not give attention to
unsuitable sight, sounds, smell, taste,
touches, sense, objects. Um you are then
the one who is practicing satipana and
subduing the worldly craving and sorrow
as the suta says and pretty much
developing the right understanding and
the and the and unobstructing that which
prevents you from having the right view.
So that's again that's why we insist so
many times like you know if you want to
practice for the right view at least you
need to be withdrawn from sensuality
like it's is simply not optional. How
can you be practicing for the right view
while not being subdued while not
subduing the worldly craving and sorrow
while still being very much engaged
controlled by the desires
uh fears griefs um passions towards the
world and sense objects. That's just two
opposite directions. You can't have it
both ways.
So then the the verses that he adds,
it's like
um it kind of reminds me even of that um
meta where it says like to protect your
mind like a mother protects her child.
like a mother protects her child.
So even if you have to go through the
crowd or go out and do this or that or
attend to things at the back of your
mind the importance of your child being
left alone there unattended is there and
you will you will quickly return to it.
You will you will spend bare minimum of
your time elsewhere
um because it means danger grows. It
increases because you left the child
unattended. So this is the same
guard your own mind accordingly so to
reach the place not yet reached. Um so
what all the Buddhas have spoken the
doctrine of a sharp sword meaning the
dharma is like a sharp sword. It just
cuts through the stuff. Um one should
unify one's mind diligently guard it and
uphold it. Uh no ordinary man in the
matters of negligence can enter such a
state the teaching of non-negligence. So
it really the verses just boil down the
whole uh point of the suta. It's about
negligence and non-negligence not about
um you know u concentrated focus on on
on a on a on a clay on a clay object or
something like that. It's like are you
choosing the negligence and not
recognizing the danger implicit in that
or are you recognizing the danger of of
of negligence and not choosing it not
willfully going towards it and it's like
those who choose the non-negligence they
are the ones that can pass into this uh
through this difficult state and little
reach deliberation. those they are still
very much choosing negligence regardless
of what practices they try to do in
order to compensate for it. If their
actions are still actions of uh
negligence, distraction, lust, aversion
and so on, there is simply no room for
them. They they can't fit through this
through this uh through this uh thin cut
that the Buddhist teaching creates the
the middle way. So I think I answered
all the points and questions that I got
either directly or indirectly.